<chapter id="introduction-sect"> <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>APBS is a software package for the numerical solution of the
    Poisson-Boltzmann equation (PBE), one of the most popular continuum models
    for describing electrostatic interactions between molecular solutes in
    salty, aqueous media. Continuum electrostatics plays an important role in
    several areas of biomolecular simulation, including:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>simulation of diffusional processes to determine ligand-protein
          and protein-protein binding kinetics,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>implicit solvent molecular dynamics of biomolecules,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>solvation and binding energy calculations to determine
          ligand-protein and protein-protein equilibrium binding constants and
          aid in rational drug design,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>and biomolecular titration studies.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    APBS was designed to efficiently evaluate electrostatic properties for
    such simulations for a wide range of length scales to enable the investigation
    of molecules with tens to millions of atoms.</para>

  <para>APBS uses <ulink url="http://www.fetk.org/">PMG</ulink> to solve the
    Poisson-Boltzmann equation numerically.  PMG is developed and maintained
    by the <ulink url="http://www.scicomp.ucsd.edu/~mholst/">Holst Research
      Group</ulink> at UC San Diego, and is designed to solve the nonlinear
    Poisson-Boltzmann equation and similar problems with linear space and time
    complexity through the use of box methods, inexact Newton methods, and
    algebraic multilevel methods.  More information about PMG may be found at
    <ulink url="http://www.fetk.org">http://www.fetk.org</ulink>.
  </para>

  <para>APBS also uses <ulink url="http://www.fetk.org/">FEtk</ulink>  to
    solve the Poisson-Boltzmann equation numerically.  FEtk is developed and
    maintained by the <ulink url="http://www.scicomp.ucsd.edu/~mholst/">Holst
    Research Group</ulink> at UC San Diego, and is designed to solve general
    coupled systems of nonlinear partial differential equations accurately and
    efficiently using adaptive multilevel finite element methods, inexact
    Newton methods, algebraic multilevel methods.   More information about
    FEtk may be found at 
    <ulink url="http://www.fetk.org">http://www.fetk.org</ulink>.
  </para>

  <formalpara> <title>Financial support</title>
    <para>The development of APBS has been supported financially by:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.nih.gov">National Institutes of 
            Health</ulink> (grant GM069702-01)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://www.npaci.edu">National Partnership for Advanced
            Computational Infrastructure</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink url="http://nbcr.sdsc.edu">National Biomedical Computation
            Resource</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </formalpara>

  <formalpara id="citing"> <title>Citing APBS</title>
    <para>
      Please acknowledge your use of APBS by citing:
      <blockquote> 
        <para> 
          <ulink url="http://www.pnas.org/cgi/content/abstract/98/18/10037"> 
            Baker NA, Sept D, Joseph S, Holst MJ, McCammon JA.  Electrostatics
            of nanosystems: application to microtubules and the ribosome.
            <citetitle>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</citetitle> 98, 10037-10041, 2001.
          </ulink>  
        </para> 
      </blockquote>
    </para>
  </formalpara>
  <formalpara id="citing2"> <title>Citing FEtk and PMG</title>
    <para>
      Please acknowledge your use of PMG and FEtk by citing:
      <blockquote> 
        <para> 
          M. Holst and F. Saied, Multigrid solution of the Poisson-Boltzmann
          equation.  <citetitle>J. Comput. Chem.</citetitle>, 14 (1993), pp.
          105-113.
        </para>
        <para>
          M. Holst and F. Saied, Numerical solution of the nonlinear
          Poisson-Boltzmann equation: Developing more robust and efficient
          methods.  <citetitle>J. Comput. Chem.</citetitle>, 16 (1995), pp.
          337-364.
        </para>
        <para>
          M. Holst, Adaptive numerical treatment of elliptic systems on
          manifolds. <citetitle>Advances in Computational
            Mathematics</citetitle>, 15 (2001), pp. 139-191.
        </para>
        <para>
          R. Bank and M. Holst, A New Paradigm for Parallel Adaptive Meshing
          Algorithms. <citetitle>SIAM Review</citetitle>, 45 (2003), pp.
          291-323.
        </para>
      </blockquote>
    </para>

  </formalpara>

  <formalpara id="authors"> <title>Contributing authors</title>
    <para>APBS was primarily written by Nathan Baker during his graduate work
      with J. Andrew McCammon and Michael Holst and extensively developed over
      the subsequent years.  APBS uses several libraries written by Mike Holst
      and members of the Holst group, including:  
      <ulink url="http://scicomp.ucsd.edu/~mholst/codes/pmg/index.html">PMG</ulink> 
      (multigrid solver for Cartesian mesh discretization), 
      <ulink url="http://www.fetk.org">FEtk</ulink> 
      (provides finite element framework, error estimators, and solvers), and 
      <ulink url="http://scicomp.ucsd.edu/~mholst/codes/maloc/index.html">MALOC
      </ulink> (hardware abstraction library for code portability).
      Additionally, a number of people have made important contributions to enhance
      APBS functionality and usability.  The full author list (in alphabetical
      order) is:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Nathan A. Baker</para>
          <para>Primary author</para> 
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Steve Bond</para>
          <para>Contributor:  FEtk library compatibility and Vopot functions</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Larry Canino</para>
          <para>Contributor: solvent accessibility function modification</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Todd Dolinsky</para>
          <para>Contributor: Python wrappers, PDB2PQR, examples, and other
          tools</para> 
        </listitem>
        <listitem> 
          <para>Adrian Elcock</para>
          <para>Contributor: parameter files</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Michael J. Holst</para>
          <para>Advisor and author of several routines scattered about APBS,
            and author of PMG (the multigrid library used by this code), author
            of MALOC (hardware abstraction library used by this code), author
            of FEtk (finite element library incorporated in developmental
            versions of this code)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Robert Konecny</para>
          <para>Contributor: parameters, CHARMM FORTRAN interface</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Jung-Hsin Lin</para>
          <para>Contributor:  OpenDX to MOLMOL conversion</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Chiansan Ma</para>
          <para>Contributor: format conversion scripts</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>J. Andrew McCammon</para>
          <para>Advisor, financial and equipment support, functionality
          suggestions</para> 
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
          <para>Jens Nielsen</para>
          <para>Contributor: PDB2PQR</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Jay Ponder</para>
          <para>Contributor:  TINKER Interface</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Michael Schnieders</para>
          <para>Contributor:  Polarizable atomic multipole routines, TINKER 
                interface</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>David Sept</para>
          <para> Contributor:  scripts and tools, VMD compatibility, general
          suggestions about functionality </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Tongye Shen</para>
          <para>Contributor:  finite element mesh generation</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </formalpara>
</chapter>
