<?xml version='1.0'?> <!-- -*- xml -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY apbsver "0.4.0">
<!ENTITY apbsdat "10 NOV 2004">
<!ENTITY license SYSTEM "license.xml">
<!ENTITY introduction SYSTEM "introduction.xml">
<!ENTITY installation SYSTEM "installation.xml">
<!ENTITY overview SYSTEM "overview.xml">
<!ENTITY using-apbs SYSTEM "using-apbs.xml">
<!ENTITY read-sect SYSTEM "read.xml">
<!ENTITY elec-sect SYSTEM "elec.xml">
<!ENTITY print-sect SYSTEM "print.xml">
<!ENTITY apbs-input SYSTEM "apbs-input.xml">
<!ENTITY programming SYSTEM "programming.xml">
<!ENTITY invocation SYSTEM "invocation.xml">
<!ENTITY getting-help SYSTEM "getting-help.xml">
<!ENTITY file-formats SYSTEM "file-formats.xml">
]>

<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>APBS &apbsver; User Guide</title>
    <subtitle>Adaptive Poisson-Boltzmann Solver</subtitle>
    <author>
      <firstname>Nathan</firstname>
      <surname>Baker</surname>
      <othername role="mi">A</othername>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Washington University in St. Louis</orgname>
        <orgdiv>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics</orgdiv>
        <orgdiv>Center for Computational Biology</orgdiv>
      </affiliation>
      <address>
        <street>700 S. Euclid Ave.</street>
        <street>Campus Box 8036</street>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>MO</state>
        <postcode>63110</postcode>
        <country>USA</country>
        <email>baker@biochem.wustl.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <copyright>
      <year>2002</year>
      <year>2003</year>
      <year>2004</year>
      <year>2005</year>
      <year>2006</year>
      <holder>Washington University in St. Louis</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
      modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published
      by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at
      your option) any later version.</para>
      <para>This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
      WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General
      Public License for more details.</para>
      <para>You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
      along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation,
      Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307 USA</para>
      <para>Linking APBS statically or dynamically with other modules is 
      making a combined work based on APBS. Thus, the terms and conditions of 
      the GNU General Public License cover the whole combination.</para>
      <para>SPECIAL GPL EXCEPTION:
      In addition, as a special exception, the copyright holders of APBS
      give you permission to combine the APBS program with free software
      programs and libraries that are released under the GNU LGPL or with
      code included in releases of ISIM, PMV, PyMOL, SMOL, VMD, and Vision.
      Such combined software may be linked with APBS and redistributed 
      together in original or modified form as mere aggregation without 
      requirement that the entire work be under the scope of the GNU General 
      Public License. This special exception permission is also extended to 
      any software listed in the SPECIAL GPL EXCEPTION clauses by the PMG, 
      FEtk, MC, or MALOC libraries.</para>
      <para>Note that people who make modified versions of APBS are not 
      obligated to grant this special exception for their modified versions; 
      it is their choice whether to do so. The GNU General Public License gives
      permission to release a modified version without this exception; this
      exception also makes it possible to release a modified version which
      carries forward this exception.</para>
    </legalnotice>
    <date>&apbsdat;</date>
    <edition>APBS version &apbsver;</edition>
  </bookinfo>

  <toc></toc>
  <!-- We are done with the preliminaries, now we can start with
          the body of the document -->

  &introduction;
  &installation;
  &overview;
  &using-apbs;
  &getting-help;
  &programming;

  &file-formats;
  &license;

</book>
      
